Guide to the Records of the New York State Federation of Women’s Clubs
Elmira College
Guide to the Records of the New York State Federation of Women’s Clubs
1898 - 2016
The bulk of the records of the New York State Federation of Women’s Clubs are papers collected during the tenure of each elected president of the organization. These papers document the history of the organization from 1898 – current. Minutes from meetings, reports of the New York Districts, Convention programs, and club events are common documents found in the presidential records. Financial records, newsletters and yearbooks of the organization are not complete. Most notably absent are records from the administrations of nine presidents including the first three: Mrs. Jennie Cunningham Croly, Mrs. William A. Montgomery and Mrs. Cornelius Zabriski.
30 linear ft. (48 Manuscript Boxes and 30 bound books)
New York State Federation of Women’s Clubs
Elmira College Archives, Gannett-Tripp Library, Elmira College, Elmira, NY
unrestricted
The New York State Federation of Women’s Clubs was organized in 1894 at the call of Sorosis, the first incorporated women’s club in the United States, also originating from New York State. Sorosis was founded in 1868 as a club organized and run by women, founded by Jane Cunningham Croly or “Jennie June” as she was more fondly known. Croly’s organization of a convention composed of women’s clubs from around the country led to the formation of the General Federation of Women’s Clubs. The ratification convention in 1890, held one year after its initial meeting in 1889, brought the organization to national prominence.
Four years later, under Mrs. Fannie I. Helmuth’s leadership and 125 delegates, the New York State Federation of Women’s Clubs was formed. Jane Cunningham Croly was promptly elected as its first president. The club incorporated in 1904.
As outlined in the certificate of incorporation, the objective of the organization was to, “bring into relationship of mutual helpfulness the various clubs of women throughout the state and to make combined action possible when deemed expedient. (Subgroup III: 1:1:2).” The favorable response to the mission of the Club spurned a rapid growth in membership, by the second annual convention in 1896, 186 clubs within the state were represented.
Education, industrial conditions, forestry, welfare work, prison reform, philanthropy, household economics and club ethics were major initiatives of the Club in the first decades of the 20th Century. By the start of World War I the Club had expanded to 461 clubs and 300,000 federated women.
During the presidency of Miss Mary Garrett Hay, 1910-1912, the rapid cultural shift could be evidenced in the club’s committee structure. The reports of the Suffrage and the Anti-Suffrage Committees exemplify the differing views of the role of women during a swiftly evolving time (Subgroup I: 8:1:1-2).
The N.Y.S.F.W.C. shifted focus to prohibition, environmental conservation and education in the 20’s and 30’s and had an increased presence during World War II, amassing bond sales to purchase an Army Bomber and ambulance, providing training for nurses and collecting books and Bibles for men in service.
In 1951 the G.F.W.C. made it mandatory for all Club members to become paying members of the G.F.W.C. The qualifications for G.F.W.C. and the financial obligations of membership reduced the membership of the N.Y.S.F.W.C.
In 1970, the Federation changed from a membership corporation to a Not-For-Profit Corporation and in July of 1978 the change in designation was adopted. Community programs, child welfare, foreign aid, prison reform, education and volunteerism were platforms for the organization over the next half century.
In 1994 the club celebrated its 100th Anniversary. The emphasis on volunteerism and community involvement has shaped the efforts of the organization into the 21st Century.
New York State Federation of Women's Clubs; General Federation of Women’s Clubs; Women—Societies and Clubs—New York (State); History—New York (State); Women volunteers in Social Service—New York (State); Civic improvement—New York (State); Women’s rights—New York (State); Business Correspondence; personal correspondence; Minutes (Records); directories; newsletters; programs (documents); periodicals; yearbooks
The records of the New York State Federation of Women’s Clubs are primarily papers concentrated on the tenure of each elected president of the organization, documenting the presidents and the history of the organization for over a century, 1898 – current. Minutes from meetings, reports of the New York Districts, Convention programs and club events are common documents found in the presidential records.
The Historian reports offer a comprehensive history of Presidential tenures and are available for a number of the Presidents. Minutes, financial records, newsletters, honor roll books and yearbooks of the organization are incomplete.
Minutes are missing from the years, 1903-1909, 1913, 1917-1941. The bulk of the financial records are from the 1940’s to the 1980’s. The New York State Federation of Women’s Clubs newsletters do not contain any long runs of publication, random volumes can be found from 1954-2015. There are two periodicals in the collection: New York State Federation News/New York State Clubwomen and Clubwomen's Life, a New York State Federation of Women’s Club publication. These publications are incomplete.
Most notably absent from the records are the papers of nine presidents including the first three: Mrs. Jennie Cunningham Croly, Mrs. William A. Montgomery and Mrs. Cornelius Zabriski.
Organizational Note:
The New York State Federation of Women’s Clubs are organized into the following Sub-Groups, Series and Sub-Series.
SERIES 1: RECORDS OF THE PRESIDENT, 1899-2016
SERIES 2: MINUTES, 1898-2008
SERIES 3: ADMINISTRATIVE RECORDS, 1902-1993
SERIES 4: FINANCIAL RECORDS, 1900-1988
SUB-SERIES 1: CHECKS, BILLS, BANK BALANCES, ETC. [1940-1988]
SUB-SERIES 2: LEDGERS [1900-1970]
SERIES 5: PUBLICATIONS, 1930-1948
SERIES 6: WRITINGS ON THE N.Y.S.F.W.C., 1898-1968, undated
SERIES 7: YEARBOOKS, 1910-1945
SERIES 8: NEWSLETTERS, 1954-2015
SERIES 9: GENERAL HISTORY OF THE N.Y.S.F.W.C., 1902-2013
SUB-SERIES 1: HISTORY OF THE N.Y.S.F.W.C. [1902-2013]
SUB-SERIES 2: HISTORY OF CLUBS [1914-2013]
SUB-SERIES 3: CONVENTION PROGRAMS
SERIES 10: HONOR ROLL, 1935-1996
SERIES 11: PHOTOGRAPHS, CLIPPINGS, EPHEMERA, 1964-1991, undated
- SERIES 1: RECORDS OF THE PRESIDENT, 1990 - 2016
- SERIES 2: Minutes [1898-2008]
- SERIES 3: ADMINISTRATIVE RECORDS [1902-1993]
- SERIES 4: FINANCIAL RECORDS, 1940 - 1970
  - SUB-SERIES 1: CHECKS, BILLS, BANK BALANCES, ETC. [1940-1988]
  - SUB-SERIES 2: LEDGERS [1900-1970]
- SERIES 5: PUBLICATIONS [1938-2008]
- SERIES 6: WRITINGS ON THE N.Y.S.F.W.C. [1898-1968, undated]
- SERIES 7: YEARBOOKS [1910-1945]
- SERIES 8: NEWSLETTERS [1954-2015]
- SERIES 9: GENERAL HISTORY OF THE N.Y.S.F.W.C. [1900-2013]
  - SUB-SERIES 1: HISTORY OF THE N.Y.S.F.W.C, 1902 - 2013
  - SUB-SERIES 2: HISTORY OF CLUBS, 1914-2013
  - SUB-SERIES 3: CONVENTION PROGRAMS, 1900-2005
- SERIES 10: HONOR ROLL [1935-1996]
- SERIES 11: PHOTOGRAPHS, CLIPPINGS, EPHEMERA [1964-1991, undated]